[
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following topologies are possible in a Wireless LAN?",
        "options": [
            "Point-to-point mode",
            "High speed mode",
            "Infrastructure-based mode",
            "Ad-hoc mode",
            "None of the other options"
        ],
        "answer": [2, 3]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Sort the exchanged messages to connect to an AP",
        "options": [],
        "answer": []
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "How does WEP key management compare to WPA/WPA2 key management?",
        "options": [
            "WEP is more efficient and faster than WPA/WPA2 in managing keys.",
            "WEP uses dynamic keys that change frequently, unlike WPA/WPA2.",
            "WEP is considered insecure due to its use of static keys, whereas WPA/WPA2 use more secure key management protocols.",
            "WEP provides stronger encryption and is more secure than WPA/WPA2.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [2]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following security services does WEP support?",
        "options": [
            "Data integrity",
            "Message confidentiality",
            "Access control",
            "Authentication",
            "None of the other options"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Why is power control important in CDMA networks?",
        "options": [
            "To enhance the data transmission speed and reduce latency.",
            "To minimize interference and improve spectral efficiency.",
            "To limit interference between adjacent cells.",
            "To conserve battery life in mobile devices.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider the maximum goodput one could reach with the following technologies. Put the following options in order from the HIGHEST to the LOWEST:",
        "options": [
            "802.11n RTS/CTS disabled, UDP + IP",
            "802.11n RTS/CTS disabled, TCP + IP",
            "802.11n RTS/CTS enabled, UDP + IP",
            "802.11n RTS/CTS enabled, TCP + IP",
            "Fast Ethernet, 100Mb/s",
            "802.11g RTS/CTS disabled, UDP + IP",
            "802.11g RTS/CTS disabled, TCP + IP",
            "802.11g RTS/CTS enabled, UDP + IP",
            "802.11g RTS/CTS enabled, TCP + IP"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]
    },
    {
        "type": "associate",
        "question": "Associate the correct definition for the following attacks in a WLAN:",
        "options": {
            "names": [
                "WEP Password cracking",
                "NAV attack",
                "Rouge Access Point",
                "De-authentication attack",
                "Chopchop attack"
            ],
            "list": [
                "Leverage the reusage of Initialization Vector to create a collision and then break the RC4 key.",
                "An attack where the attacker manipulates the frame duration value to prevent other devices from accessing the channel.",
                "A fake AP that impersonates the real AP.",
                "The attacker sends forged de-authentication frames to force a STA to repeat the connection process.",
                "The process to recover the plaintext content of a frame by replaying a portion of the original frame."
            ]
        },
        "answer": {
            "WEP Password cracking": "Leverage the reusage of Initialization Vector to create a collision and then break the RC4 key.",
            "NAV attack": "An attack where the attacker manipulates the frame duration value to prevent other devices from accessing the channel.",
            "Rouge Access Point": "A fake AP that impersonates the real AP.",
            "De-authentication attack": "The attacker sends forged de-authentication frames to force a STA to repeat the connection process.",
            "Chopchop attack": "The process to recover the plaintext content of a frame by replaying a portion of the original frame."
        }
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following best describes a NAV attack in WiFi networks?",
        "options": [
            "An attack where the attacker decrypts the communication between two devices.",
            "An attack where the attacker sends excessive data packets to the network, causing a denial of service.",
            "An attack where the attacker sets a very short NAV value to prevent other devices from accessing the channel.",
            "An attack where the attacker manipulates the NAV value to prevent other devices from accessing the channel.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [3]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following information would an attacker require to mount a de-authentication attack against one specific STA in a WLAN?",
        "options": [
            "The AP MAC address",
            "The STA MAC address",
            "The WLAN channel",
            "The WLAN ESSID",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Why in 802.11 there are two destination mac addresses?",
        "options": [
            "The first indicates the AP that has to receive the frame. The second indicates the interface of the router that frame is destined to.",
            "To correctly identify the STA sending the frame.",
            "For anonymisation.",
            "For error correction.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [0]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Why in 802.11 there are two destination mac addresses?",
        "options": [
            "In case there are multiple APs, to indicate the two APs that should receive and process the frame.",
            "For error correction",
            "For anonymisation",
            "None of the other options.",
            "To correctly identify the STA sending the frame"
        ],
        "answer": [3]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "What type of encryption does OWE use to secure data in transit?",
        "options": [
            "Diffie-Hellman key exchange to establish a shared secret.",
            "Asymmetric encryption using RSA keys.",
            "Symmetric key encryption with a pre-shared key.",
            "None of the other options.",
            "Static encryption keys manually configured by the user."
        ],
        "answer": [0]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider two STA, A and B, that belong to a WLAN managed by an AP. RTS/CTS are DISABLED. A and B wake up at the same time to send a data frame, creating thus a collision. Put in the right sequence the frames and events that could occur in time.",
        "options": [
            "A sends a DATA(A) frame",
            "B sends a DATA(B) frame",
            "DATA(A) collides with DATA(B)",
            "A and B wait for the AP's ACK",
            "Neither A nor B received the ACK, so they backoff",
            "A waits 10ms and tries to retransmit DATA(A)",
            "B waits 20ms and listens to the channel, sensing its busy with DATA(A) transmission",
            "AP receives DATA(A)",
            "AP sends an ACK to A"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider two STA, A and B, that belong to a WLAN managed by an AP. RTS/CTS are ENABLED. A and B wake up at the same time to send a data frame, creating thus a collision. Put in the right sequence the frames and events that could occur in time.",
        "options": [
            "A sends a RTS",
            "B sends a RTS",
            "RTS sent by A collides with RTS sent by B",
            "A waits 10ms and tries to retransmit the RTS",
            "B waits 20ms and tries to retransmit the RTS",
            "AP receives the RTS from A and sends a CTS(A)",
            "A and B receive the CTS(AP)",
            "A sends a DATA frame while B defers its transmission",
            "AP sends an ACK to A"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider the case a STA would like to transmit a frame to the AP. No other transmissions are present. RTS/CTS are disabled. Put in the correct order over time the sequence of events that would occur:",
        "options": [
            "A waits for DIFS time",
            "A sends the DATA(A) frame",
            "AP receives the DATA(A) frame",
            "AP waits for SIFS time",
            "AP sends ACK to A",
            "A receives the ACK and transmits a second frame"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Consider a STA trying to connect to an AP. In which order the following frames are exchanged?",
        "options": [
            "ACK",
            "Beacon",
            "Probe",
            "Authentication",
            "Association",
            "Data"
        ],
        "answer": [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 0]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Suppose you are at home with your laptop and a set of WiFi USB adapters. How can you know the capabilities of your NICs?",
        "options": [
            "Use a WiFi scanning tool to analyze the available networks.",
            "Refer to the technical documentation provided by the NIC manufacturer.",
            "Contact your ISP for information about the NICs capabilities.",
            "Look into the configuration settings of your home router.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following information would you need to analyze to assess the capabilities of a given NIC?",
        "options": [
            "The MAC address",
            "Supported frequency bands",
            "Supported protocols and standards (e.g., 802.11n, 802.11ac)",
            "Transmit power",
            "All of the above"
        ],
        "answer": [4]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Why in 802.11 there are two destination mac addresses?",
        "options": [
            "The first indicates the AP that has to receive the frame. The second indicates the interface of the router that frame is destined to.",
            "To correctly identify the STA sending the frame.",
            "For anonymisation.",
            "For error correction.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [0]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Why in 802.11 there are two destination mac addresses?",
        "options": [
            "In case there are multiple APs, to indicate the two APs that should receive and process the frame.",
            "For error correction",
            "For anonymisation",
            "None of the other options.",
            "To correctly identify the STA sending the frame"
        ],
        "answer": [3]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "What type of encryption does OWE use to secure data in transit?",
        "options": [
            "Diffie-Hellman key exchange to establish a shared secret.",
            "Asymmetric encryption using RSA keys.",
            "Symmetric key encryption with a pre-shared key.",
            "None of the other options.",
            "Static encryption keys manually configured by the user."
        ],
        "answer": [0]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider two STA, A and B, that belong to a WLAN managed by an AP. RTS/CTS are DISABLED. A and B wake up at the same time to send a data frame, creating thus a collision. Put in the right sequence the frames and events that could occur in time.",
        "options": [
            "A sends a DATA(A) frame",
            "B sends a DATA(B) frame",
            "DATA(A) collides with DATA(B)",
            "A and B wait for the AP's ACK",
            "Neither A nor B received the ACK, so they backoff",
            "A waits 10ms and tries to retransmit DATA(A)",
            "B waits 20ms and listens to the channel, sensing its busy with DATA(A) transmission",
            "AP receives DATA(A)",
            "AP sends an ACK to A"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider two STA, A and B, that belong to a WLAN managed by an AP. RTS/CTS are ENABLED. A and B wake up at the same time to send a data frame, creating thus a collision. Put in the right sequence the frames and events that could occur in time.",
        "options": [
            "A sends a RTS",
            "B sends a RTS",
            "RTS sent by A collides with RTS sent by B",
            "A waits 10ms and tries to retransmit the RTS",
            "B waits 20ms and tries to retransmit the RTS",
            "AP receives the RTS from A and sends a CTS(A)",
            "A and B receive the CTS(AP)",
            "A sends a DATA frame while B defers its transmission",
            "AP sends an ACK to A"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider the case a STA would like to transmit a frame to the AP. No other transmissions are present. RTS/CTS are disabled. Put in the correct order over time the sequence of events that would occur:",
        "options": [
            "A waits for DIFS time",
            "A sends the DATA(A) frame",
            "AP receives the DATA(A) frame",
            "AP waits for SIFS time",
            "AP sends ACK(A)",
            "The transmission is completed"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Consider the case a STA would like to transmit a frame to the AP. No other transmissions are present. RTS/CTS are ENABLED. Put in the correct order over time the sequence of events that would occur:",
        "options": [
            "A waits for DIFS time",
            "A sends RTS",
            "AP received RTS and wait SIFS time",
            "AP sends CTS",
            "A receives CTS and waits SIFS time",
            "A sends the DATA(A) frame",
            "AP receives the DATA(A) frame",
            "AP waits for SIFS time",
            "AP sends ACK(A)",
            "The transmission is completed"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Why in a WLAN it is not sufficient to use the CSMA-CD protocol used in Ethernet?",
        "options": [
            "It will be impossible to detect an eventual collision by the transmitter because the transmitted signal power would be much stronger than the received signal power.",
            "The WLAN transmitter can either transmit or receive, making it impossible to detect collisions when they occur.",
            "CSMA-CD requires a bidirectional channel to work. In WLAN there is only one single shared channel.",
            "CSMA-CD requires an additional channel to signal collisions.",
            "None of the other options"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following are effective defenses against deauthentication attacks in WiFi networks?",
        "options": [
            "Disabling encryption to improve performance.",
            "Honour only de-authentication requests that have the same physical layer properties of other messages sent by such a STA.",
            "Honour de-authentication requests only from STAs that remain idle for the next 15 seconds.",
            "Ignoring de-authentication frames entirely.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1, 2, 3]
    },
    {
        "type": "order",
        "question": "Put in the correct order the messages the station and the AP exchange before starting the data exchange:",
        "options": [
            "AP send the Beacon",
            "STA sends the Probe request",
            "AP sends the Probe response",
            "STA sends the Authentication request",
            "AP sends the Authentication response",
            "STA sends the Association request",
            "AP sends the Association response"
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Select the TRUE answers among the following ones about the purposes of CSMA-CA in wireless networking.",
        "options": [
            "It tries to prevent collisions during data transmission.",
            "It ensures all devices have equal access to the wireless medium.",
            "It cannot prevent collisions entirely, especially in high-density networks.",
            "It encrypts data packets for secure transmission.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [0, 1, 2]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following security features does Simultaneous Authentication of Equals (SAE) provide?",
        "options": [
            "Stronger message authentication via MIC instead of CRC.",
            "Protection against man-in-the-middle attacks.",
            "Protection against offline dictionary attacks.",
            "Mutual authentication between devices.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1, 2, 3]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "What is the primary purpose of the 'Duration' field in the WiFi protocol header?",
        "options": [
            "To indicate the duration of a data transmission.",
            "To reserve the wireless medium for a specified period to avoid collisions.",
            "To specify the length of time a device can transmit data.",
            "To define the time interval during which the channel is busy.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "How is the value for the 'Duration' field typically calculated in WiFi networks?",
        "options": [
            "Determined by the physical distance between the devices.",
            "Defined by the number of wireless devices currently connected to the access point.",
            "Calculated according to the duration of the current transmission plus any additional time needed for acknowledgments.",
            "Based on the data rate of the transmission.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [2]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following provides a possible classification of a wireless communication system?",
        "options": [
            "High speed networks",
            "Fixed or mobile",
            "Infrastructure or Ad Hoc network",
            "Wireless Wide Area Networks or Wireless Local Area Networks",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1, 2, 3]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "What is the primary purpose of SIFS (Short Inter-Frame Space) in WiFi networks?",
        "options": [
            "To synchronize clocks between different wireless devices.",
            "To prioritize time-sensitive transmissions like acknowledgements (ACK).",
            "To speed up data communications.",
            "To encrypt data packets for secure transmission.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [4]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "Which of the following statements correctly describes the difference between deauthentication and disassociation attacks in WiFi networks?",
        "options": [
            "Deauthentication attacks involve intercepting and decrypting communication, while disassociation attacks involve jamming the wireless signal.",
            "Deauthentication attacks force devices to disconnect by sending fake deauthentication frames, while disassociation attacks force devices to disconnect by sending fake disassociation frames.",
            "Deauthentication attacks force devices to disconnect by sending fake deauthentication frames, while disassociation attacks force devices to reconnect by sending fake association frames.",
            "Deauthentication attacks gain unauthorized access by cracking the encryption key, while disassociation attacks flood the network with excessive traffic.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "How does rate adaptation contribute to enhancing network performance in WiFi networks?",
        "options": [
            "By reducing the latency in transmitting data packets.",
            "By ensuring devices can adjust their data rates based on changing environmental conditions.",
            "By minimizing interference from neighbouring wireless networks.",
            "By synchronizing clocks between devices to avoid timing conflicts.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "How is the Pairwise Master Key (PMK) typically generated in WPA networks?",
        "options": [
            "It is manually entered by the network administrator.",
            "It is derived from the user's passphrase and other material that makes it unique for each STA connected in the WLAN.",
            "It is derived from the user's passphrase and other material that makes it identical for all STA connected in the WLAN.",
            "It is automatically generated by the access point during the initial setup.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "What is the hidden terminal problem in WiFi networks?",
        "options": [
            "A situation where a wireless device is physically hidden and cannot connect to the access point.",
            "An issue where wireless devices within the same range of an access point cannot hear each other's transmissions, leading to potential collisions and packet loss.",
            "A scenario where two wireless devices cannot communicate directly with each other due to obstacles in their line of sight.",
            "A condition where the access point's signal is too weak for devices to establish a stable connection.",
            "None of the other options."
        ],
        "answer": [1]
    },
    {
        "type": "associate",
        "question": "Associate the correct definition of the following terms:",
        "options": [
            "Association request",
            "Authentication request",
            "Probe request",
            "Beacon"
        ],
        "answers": [
            "A frame the station sends to the AP to enable the communication in the WLAN",
            "A frame the station sends to the AP to provide its identity and request access to the WLAN.",
            "A request frame the station sends to look for the presence of a WLAN AP.",
            "A broadcast message sent to advertise the presence and capabilities of a WLAN."
        ]
    },
    {
        "type": "associate",
        "question": "Associate the correct definition of the following terms as defined in 802.11x:",
        "options": [
            "Supplicant",
            "Port",
            "Authentication Server",
            "Authentication system"
        ],
        "answers": [
            "A device that wishes to attach to the LAN/WLAN.",
            "Physical or logical system that allows or blocks the data communication of a device.",
            "A trusted server that receives and responds to requests for network access, and can tell the authenticator if the connection is to be allowed.",
            "A network device that provides a data link between the client and the network. It can allow or block network traffic between the two."
        ]
    },
    {
        "type": "multiple-choice",
        "question": "What is the primary purpose of Opportunistic Wireless Encryption (OWE)?",
        "options": [
            "To improve data transmission speed by encrypting data.",
            "To manage the distribution of encryption keys manually.",
            "To provide data encryption for open networks without user intervention.",
            "None of the previous options",
            "To strengthen the security provided by previous protocols by supporting keys up to 256 bits."
        ],
        "answer": [2]
    }
]
    